Finding Aid for Arthur Dunham Papers ca. 1900-1980
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Arthur Dunham Papers circa 1900-1980
Dunham, Arthur.
85623 Aa 2
Social worker in Massachusetts and Pennsylvania, professor of community organization at the University of Michigan, a pacifist imprisoned as a conscientious objector during World War I, a founding member of Ann Arbor Society of Friends. Papers include correspondence, subject files and research material relating to his work and teaching, files assembled for a history of the Ann Arbor Friends Meeting, material on his pacifist activities and published and unpublished writings.
32.2 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Arthur Dunham and came to the library in two major accessions, 1973 and 1980. Donor no. 5344
The collection is open to research. In 1973, Arthur Dunham stipulated that the names of individuals used in his World War I reminiscences could not be cited.
Arthur Dunham was born in St. Louis, Missouri, on August 3, 1893. He graduated from Washington University in St. Louis in 1914, and obtained an M.A. in political science from the University of Illinois in 1917. Dunham started as a social worker in 1915 at a neighborhood center in St. Louis. Later in 1917, he became a family case worker for the St. Louis Provident Association.
Dunham's career was interrupted in 1918 as a result of America's entry into World War I. Dunham was a religious pacifist and refused service when drafted in July 1918. Incarcerated at Fort Riley until his court-martial on November 12, 1918, Dunham was sentenced to 25 years of hard labor. He remained in prison at Fort Leavenworth until his sentence was overturned on January 27, 1919. On May 31, 1919, Dunham married Esther Schneider, who had strongly influenced him to take his stand as a conscientious objector.
From September 1919 to May 1923, Dunham worked as secretary of the Philadelphia Social Service Exchange. From 1923 to 1925, he was secretary of the Newton (Massachusetts) Central Council, an organization of social agencies. In 1925 he became secretary of the Child Welfare Division of the Public Charities Association of Pennsylvania. He remained in this position until 1935. He also held temporary positions during this period with the Pittsburgh Child Welfare Study, the Family Welfare Association, and the Pennsylvania State Emergency Relief Board.
Dunham was appointed professor of community organization at the University of Michigan in 1935, holding this post until his retirement in 1963. At the university, Dunham taught courses in community organization and social welfare administration. From 1962 to 1972 he held posts as a visiting professor at a number of universities. In 1956 he made a trip through Europe and Asia, spending three months in India where he studied their community development programs. Dunham also made a trip to Northern Ireland in 1971 to serve as a consultant to the Northern Ireland Community Relations Commission.
Arthur and Esther Dunham joined the Society of Friends in 1923. In 1935 they were instrumental in founding the Ann Arbor Friends Meeting. They remained very active in the Meeting, and in 1975 Dunham wrote a history of its first forty years.
Dunham died September 1, 1980.
Summary Contents List
Biographical and autobiographical material (box 1)
Rosters (correspondence, reports, memos, etc.) (boxes 1-3)
Correspondence (box 3)
Ann Arbor Friends Meeting (boxes 4-6)
General (box 4)
Dunham's history (includes manuscript of history and Dunham's subject file) (boxes 4 6)
Society of Friends (box 6)
Associations (boxes 6-11)
Newton (Massachusetts) Central Council (boxes 6 7)
Public Charities Association of Pennsylvania (boxes 7 9)
Philadelphia Social Service Exchange (box 10)
Pittsburgh Social Service Exchange (box 10)
Social Service Exchanges (box 10)
Association for the Study of Community Organization (box 10)
National Association of Social Workers (includes oral history) (boxes 10 11)
Miscellaneous associations (box 11)
Agency studies (boxes 12-12)
Course outlines (box 13)
Community Development (boxes 13-17)
Subject file (boxes 13-16)
Courses (boxes 16-17)
Community Organization (boxes 20-22)
Subject file (boxes 17-19)
Courses (boxes 19-20)
Social Welfare Administration
Subject file (boxes 20-21)
Courses (boxes 21-22)
Public Welfare (box 23
Conscientious Objection (boxes 23-24)
Travel (box 24)
Work reports (boxes 24-25)
Social work - Social welfare (box 25)
Osborn, Curtis (Diary, Jane Wayland Children's Home, Phoenix, Arizona) (boxes 25-26)
Topical file (boxes 26-27)
Unpublished manuscripts (boxes 27-28)
Published material (boxes 28-32)
Photographs (box 33)
The Arthur Dunham papers are a valuable source for the study of the evolution of social work theory and practice, particularly in the area of community development and organization. In addition, the collection details Dunham's experience as a World War I conscientious objector, as well as including much information on the Ann Arbor Friends Meeting.
Subjects:
Child welfare--Michigan.; Conscientious objectors.; Friends Meetinghouse (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Pacifism--United States.; Social service--United States.; Society of Friends--Michigan.; Ann Arbor Friends Meeting (Ann Arbor, Mich.); University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan. School of Social Work.; World War, 1914-1918.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Community service.; Conscientious objectors.; Detention facilities.; Dunham, Arthur, 1893-; Dunham, Ruth.; Friends Meetinghouse (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Ann Arbor Friends Meeting (Ann Arbor, Mich.); World War, 1914-1918.
Contributors:
Osborn, Curtis.
Genre/Form:
Photographs.
- Biographical and autobiographical material
  The Biographical and Autobiographical Material series, in addition to vita of both Arthur and Esther Dunham, includes a set of the family Christmas letters written over the period of 1923 to 1980 and an extensive manuscript entitled "Our Family" by Esther Dunham.
  - Vita (Box 1)
  - Biographical material (Box 1)
  - Biographical clippings (Box 1)
  - Autobiographical sketch of Arthur and Esther Dunham (Box 1)
  - Biographical notes, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Genealogical papers (Box 1)
  - Family Christmas letters
    - 1923-1953 (Box 1)
    - 1954-1980 (Box 1)
  - Log books (Box 1)
  - Esther S. Dunham Vita and biographical material (Box 1)
  - "Our Family" by Esther Dunham (manuscript), 4 folders (Box 1)
- Rosters
  (correspondence, reports, memos, etc.)
  Although the nature of most series are clear from the title given them, others require explanation. The series labeled Rosters documents Dunham's activities from the 1920s through the 1970s. "Rosters" is the term used by Dunham, and in this series, he placed correspondence, memos, reports, and ephemera. Significantly, from the 1950s to his death, the "Roster" series was almost exclusively correspondence. The researcher should thus note that for this period the roster files are a more complete series of correspondence than the Correspondence series itself. The Rosters series is made up of a chronologically arranged subseries as well as separate subseries of "Rosters" relating to various posts Dunham held as visiting professor.
  - General
    - 1920s, 1930-May 1970, 25 folders (Box 1)
    - June 1970-1979, 20 folders (Box 2)
  - University of Missouri
    - 1963-August 1965, 12 folders (Box 2)
  - Richmond Technical Institute
    - August 1966-January 1967 (Box 2)
    - February 1967-June 1967, 3 folders (Box 3)
  - Ann Arbor
    - June 1965-December 1969, 7 folders (Box 3)
  - Manchester, England
    - September-December 1967 (Box 3)
  - Fresno State University
    - January 1968-June 1968, 3 folders (Box 3)
- Correspondence
  The Correspondence series, as noted, should be used with the Rosters series for Dunham correspondence. The series includes a chronological subseries dated 1915 to 1980 and two alphabetical subseries dated 1958 to 1978.
  - Chronological
    - Undated, 1915-1926 (Box 3)
    - 1932-1980, 6 folders (Box 3)
  - Alphabetical
    - circa 1958-1963 A-Z, 3 folders (Box 3)
    - circa 1967-1978 A-Z, 5 folders (Box 3)
  - Letters of congratulation
    - On receiving position at University of Michigan 1935 (Box 3)
    - On retirement from the University of Michigan 1962, 3 folders (Box 3)
- Ann Arbor Friends Meeting
  The Ann Arbor Friends Meeting series contains two subseries. The first contains general materials relating to the Meeting. The second is a subject file of materials assembled by Dunham for his history of the Meeting.
  - General
    - "Growth of a Friend's Meeting" by Esther Dunham (Box 4)
    - Annual Newsletters (Box 4)
    - Bulletins and calendars
      - 1955, 1962, 1967 (Box 4)
      - 1968-1969 (Box 4)
      - 1970, 1973-1974 (Box 4)
      - 1975-1976 (Box 4)
      - 1977 (Box 4)
      - 1978 (Box 4)
      - 1979 (Box 4)
    - Welcome sheets and News notes
      - Undated, 1975 (Box 4)
      - 1976 (Box 4)
      - 1977 (Box 4)
      - 1978-1979 (Box 4)
    - Minutes 1937-1941 (Box 4)
    - 40th Anniversary celebration (Box 4)
    - Membership
      - General (Box 4)
      - 1937-1953, 1969 (Box 4)
      - 1972 (Box 4)
    - New Meetinghouse (Box 4)
    - Conscientious Objectors (Box 4)
    - Business Meeting May 16, 1965 (Box 4)
    - Meeting Histories (Box 4)
    - Records (Bentley Library) (Box 4)
    - Speaking material, 5 folders (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 4)
  - Dunham's History of Ann Arbor Friends Meeting
    - "Ann Arbor Friends Meeting: 1935-1975" by Arthur Dunham (Box 4)
    - Historical subject file
      - Abortion-activities (Box 4)
      - Adoptions-Alcohol (Box 4)
      - AFFC-AFSC (Box 4)
      - Announcements-Beginnings (Box 4)
      - Bennett-Boulding (Box 4)
      - Boycott-Building (Box 4)
      - Bulletin-Camp (Box 4)
      - Campus-Children (Box 4)
      - Christmas-Clothing (Box 4)
      - Cloverdale-Conflict (Box 4)
      - C.O.'s-Corporation (Box 4)
      - Costa Rica-Dennis Morley (Box 4)
      - Detroit Friends School-Dubois (Box 5)
      - Easter-Fellowship Church (Box 5)
      - Fellowship-Finances (Box 5)
      - Five Years Meeting-Friendly Anthology (Box 5)
      - Friends characteristics-Friends groups (Box 5)
      - Friends Lake Community-Friends meetings (Box 5)
      - Friends Organizations-Gandhi (Box 5)
      - Green Pastures-Guests (Box 5)
      - Halloween-Hiroshima (Box 5)
      - History-Incorporation (Box 5)
      - Individual reactions-Jackson Friends Groups (Box 5)
      - Jackson Fund-Knight (Box 5)
      - Lake Erie Yearly Meetings (Box 5)
      - Leonard-Marriage (Box 5)
      - Meeting House-Meetings (Box 5)
      - Meetings (cont.) (Box 5)
      - Meetings for Worship-Membership (Box 5)
      - Membership (affiliate)-Minutes (Box 5)
      - Monthly Bulletin-Older (Box 5)
      - Organization-Outside visitors (Box 5)
      - Pastoral function-Peace (Box 5)
      - Peace education-Prisons (Box 5)
      - Problems-Quaker Training Center (Box 5)
      - Quarterly Meeting-Race relations (Box 5)
      - Radical discipleship-Scattergood School (Box 5)
      - Seekers-Social welfare (Box 5)
      - Solstis School-Stepping Stone School (Box 6)
      - Student counselor-Travels (Box 6)
      - United Nations-Which Way the Wind (Box 6)
      - Willard, Nancy-Worship (Box 6)
      - Worship (fellowship group)-Young marrieds (Box 6)
- Society of Friends
  The Society of Friends series contains material relating to Friends activities on the regional and national levels.
  - Green Pastures Quarterly Meeting undated, 1957-1979, 3 folders (Box 6)
  - Lake Erie Association bulletins, undated 1962, 1969-1979, 4 folders (Box 6)
  - Lake Erie Association Miscellaneous (Box 6)
  - American Friends Service Committee
    - Refugee Committee (Box 6)
    - Publications, 2 folders (Box 6)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 6)
  - Pendle Hill
    - 1941-1942, 2 folders (Box 6)
    - 1973-1979 (Box 6)
  - Friends World Committee (Box 6)
  - "Goals of a Friends Meeting" (article) (Box 6)
  - Marriage (Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 6)
- Associations
  The Associations series includes very detailed chronological records of the activities of the Newton Central Council and the Public Charities Association (PCA) of Pennsylvania during Dunham's tenure with these organizations. The Newton Central Council case record is arranged by page number and accessible by a table of contents. The PCA material includes two principal subseries, one including minutes, reports, and agenda and the other including scrapbooks assembled by Dunham which reflect the activities of the PCA. Both of these subseries are arranged by date.
  Also notable in the Associations series is the National Association of Social Workers material. This includes transcripts of an oral history interview with Dunham that includes extensive biographical and organizational information. Also within this series is a file for the Michigan Council of Churches Committee on Race Relations with material dating from 1943 to 1945 which may be of interest to students of early approaches to civil rights.
  - Newton Central Council
    - Case record 1923-1925, 19 folders (Box 6)
    - Community organization (Box 6)
    - Social planning, 7 folders (Box 7)
    - Printed materials (Box 7)
  - Public Charities Association of Pennsylvania
    - Minutes, reports, agenda September 1933-October 1935, 8 folders (Box 7)
    - Reports 1942-1945 (Box 7)
    - Dunham's office diary 1925-1931 (Box 7)
    - Scrapbooks of Public Charities Association Materials (in folders)
      - 1924-April 1931, 28 folders (Box 7)
      - May 1931-September 1935, 27 folders (Box 8)
  - Family & Child Welfare Division
    - Scrapbooks (in folders) (Box 8)
      - December 1932-November 1934, 14 folders (Box 8)
  - Mothers' Assistance Campaign
    - Scrapbooks (in folders) (Box 8)
      - October 1926-October 1927, 6 folders (Box 8)
    - Case History 1931-1932 (Box 8)
  - Child Welfare Division
    - Papers (Box 8)
  - Ten Year Child Welfare Program
    - Case History 1929 (Box 8)
    - Case History. 1930 (Box 9)
    - Exhibits 1928-January 1931, 4 folders (Box 9)
    - Harrisburg Conference 1930, 2 folders (Box 9)
    - Publications (Box 9)
  - Reports and published material
    - Reports (Box 9)
      - Government relief (Box 9)
      - Child care in Delaware County (Box 9)
    - Printed material
      - Undated, 1923-1957, 12 folders (Box 9)
      - P.C.A. Herald 1937-1949 (Box 9)
      - Miscellaneous, 1 file box (Box 9)
  - Philadelphia Social Service Exchange
    - General (Box 10)
    - Summaries 1912-1939 (Box 10)
    - Publicity and forms, 2 folders (Box 10)
    - Reorganization (Box 10)
    - Office manual 1923, 9 folders (Box 10)
    - Printed material (Box 10)
  - Pittsburgh Social Service Exchange
    - Papers (Box 10)
  - Social Service Exchanges
    - General (Box 10)
    - Addresses and papers by Dunham (Box 10)
    - Literature (Box 10)
    - Scrapbook, 3 folders (Box 10)
  - Association for the Study of Community Organization
    - Appeal letters (Box 10)
    - Meetings (Box 10)
    - History (Box 10)
    - Newsletter (Box 10)
    - Progress reports, 2 folders (Box 10)
    - Scrapbook, 5 folders (Box 10)
    - Miscellaneous, 2 folders (Box 10)
  - National Association of Social Workers
    - Oral History Reference, 3 folders (Box 10)
    - Oral History Interview with Dunham-transcripts, 2 volumes (Box 11)
  - American Association of Retired Persons
    - Chapter Handbook (Box 11)
    - Correspondence (Box 11)
    - Finance (Box 11)
    - Nash, Bernard E. (Box 11)
    - Pamphlet (Box 11)
    - Reference (Box 11)
    - Report (Box 11)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 11)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Newark Advancement Committee 1919 (Box 11)
    - Family Welfare Association of America 1932 (Box 11)
    - Michigan Welfare and Relief Study Commission 1936-1937, 2 folders (Box 11)
    - Michigan Welfare and Relief Study Commission report, 1 volumes (Box 11)
    - Joint Vocational Service, Vocational Service for Social Workers Report 1939, 1 volumes (Box 11)
    - National Society for Crippled Children 1942 (Box 11)
    - American Association of Schools of Social Work 1943 (Box 11)
    - Michigan Council of Churches, Committee on Race Relations
      - Case history 1943 (Box 11)
      - Case history 1944 (Box 11)
      - Minutes 1943-1944 (Box 11)
      - Handbook 1945 (Box 11)
    - United Community Defense Services 1945-1955, 2 folders (Box 11)
    - Ann Arbor Council of Social Agencies Self evaluations 1949-1950 (Box 11)
    - Council on Social Work Education 1961 (Box 11)
    - University of Missouri Center for Community Development 1964 (Box 11)
    - Michigan Welfare League pamphlets 1966-1969 (Box 11)
- Agency studies
  The Agency Studies series includes reports and other documentation about surveys and studies in which Dunham participated or in which he was interested. Prominent in this series are the Pittsburgh Child Welfare Study, 1929-1930 and a study undertaken for the Welfare Council of New York City in 1948.
  - White-Williams Foundation 1922 (Box 12)
  - Social Service Exchanges Survey reports 1923-1924, 2 folders (Box 12)
  - Pittsburgh Child Welfare Study 1929-1930
    - Section reports, 4 folders (Box 12)
    - Office manual, 2 folders (Box 12)
    - Agency reports, 2 folders (Box 12)
    - Pamphlets (Box 12)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 12)
  - Joint Vocational Service 1938-1939, 2 folders (Box 12)
  - Detroit Consultation Bureau 1945-1946, 2 folders (Box 12)
  - Welfare Council of New York City 1948
    - Final report (Box 12)
    - Section reports, 8 folders (Box 12)
    - Scrapbooks, 13 folders (Box 12)
    - Working materials, 3 folders (Box 12)
    - Reference Memoranda (Box 13)
    - Miscellaneous, 2 folders (Box 13)
  - Women's International League for Peace and Freedom 1955, 2 folders (Box 13)
- Course outlines
  Course Outlines have arranged by course topic and them chronologically. This series should be used jointly with the following series for documentation of the content of Dunham courses.
  - Community Organization 1935-1962, 15 folders (Box 13)
    (different course numbers; some gaps in dates)
  - Administration 1959-1962, 3 folders (Box 13)
  - Seminar 1955-1959, 8 folders (Box 13)
  - Community Welfare Councils
    - 1952-1953 (Box 13)
    - 1954-1955 (Box 13)
  - Social Services 1958-1960, 2 folders (Box 13)
  - Summer Institute 1952 (Box 13)
  - Public Welfare 1962-1963 (Box 13)
  - Independent Study 1968 (Box 13)
  - Special studies for International Students 1958-1959 (Box 13)
  - Miscellaneous, 2 folders (Box 13)
- Community Development
  The series labeled Community Development was organized by Dunham into subseries reflecting the use which he made of these materials. The series includes a subject file subseries apparently used by Dunham for his personal reference and a course subseries with information about the courses Dunham taught in this area.
  - Subject file
    - Administration (Box 13)
    - Afro-Asian Rural Reconstruction Organization (Box 13)
    - Alaska (Box 13)
    - Antigonish (Box 14)
    - Barrio Planning handbook (Box 14)
    - Bibliography (Box 14)
    - Bibliography-Dunham (Box 14)
    - Biddle, William (Box 14)
    - Case materials (Box 14)
    - Case materials-Du Sautoy (Box 14)
    - Community Development Foundation (Box 14)
    - Community Development Journal (Box 14)
    - Community Development Society (Box 14)
    - Community Organization-Relationships (Box 14)
    - Community Study (Box 14)
    - Connor, Desmond M. (Box 14)
    - Cooperative Communities (Box 14)
    - Countries (Box 14)
    - Courses, 3 folders (Box 14)
    - Courses-Administration (Box 14)
    - Criticism (Willard Johnson) (Box 14)
    - Culture (Box 14)
    - Curriculum (Box 14)
    - Evaluation (Box 14)
    - Evaluation (Ellen Biddle) (Box 14)
    - Films (Box 14)
    - Group-Group dynamics (Box 14)
    - Illustrations and Quotations (Box 14)
    - India (Box 14)
    - Indians-American (Box 14)
    - International Society for C.D. (Box 14)
    - Lectures and papers
      - 1957-1958 (Box 14)
      - 1962 (Box 14)
      - 1963-1965 (Box 14)
      - 1966 (Box 14)
      - 1967-1971 (Box 14)
      - 1972 (Box 14)
    - Lectures-School of Education 1975 (Box 14)
    - Looseleaf (Box 14)
    - Menlo, Allen, 3 folders (Box 14)
    - Methods and skills (Box 14)
    - Michigan, University of-Proposed course (Box 14)
    - Missouri, University of, 2 folders (Box 15)
    - Nature (Box 15)
    - North America (Box 15)
    - North America-Report to U.N. (Box 15)
    - Outlook (Box 15)
    - Outlook-Symposium, letters (Box 15)
    - Personnel (Box 15)
    - Personnel-Types of jobs (Box 15)
    - Principles (Box 15)
    - Problems (Box 15)
    - Research (Box 15)
    - Social science (Box 15)
    - Social work (Box 15)
    - Songs (Box 15)
    - Southern Illinois University (Box 15)
    - Speaking material (Box 15)
    - Tampoulon, Mulia-"Prosperous Village" (Box 15)
    - Teaching notes, 7 folders (Box 15)
    - Training (Box 15)
    - Travel and book (Box 15)
    - United Nations (Box 15)
    - United States (Box 15)
    - Urban (Box 15)
    - Miscellaneous, 5 folders (Box 16)
  - Courses
    - General, 4 folders (Box 16)
    - Case materials (Box 16)
    - Personnel (Box 16)
    - Alaska 1966, 2 folders (Box 16)
    - Alaska Methodist University, 2 folders (Box 16)
    - Georgia, University of (Box 16)
    - Hawaii (Box 16)
    - Michigan, Fall 1960-1961 (Box 16)
    - Michigan January 1966 (Box 16)
    - Missouri, University of, AID African Program, 5 folders (Box 16)
    - Seminars
      - Michigan 1960-1961, 3 folders (Box 16)
      - Michigan 1962, 3 folders (Box 16)
      - Michigan 1963, 3 folders (Box 16)
    - Workshops
      - Alaska 1966, 9 folders (Box 16)
      - Association for International Development (Box 17)
      - Michigan-Mali workers, 2 folders (Box 17)
      - Missouri 1964, 2 folders (Box 17)
      - Missouri 1965, 3 folders (Box 17)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 17)
- Community Organization
  The series labeled Community Organization was organized by Dunham into subseries reflecting the use which he made of these materials. The series includes a subject file subseries apparently used by Dunham for his personal reference and a course subseries with information about the courses Dunham taught in this area.
  - Subject file
    - Activities (Box 17)
    - Aging (Box 17)
    - Analysis (Box 17)
    - Bibliography-Dunham, 3 folders (Box 17)
    - Boards (Box 17)
    - Case materials, 2 folders (Box 17)
    - Centralization (Box 17)
    - Child welfare (Box 17)
    - Church (Box 17)
    - Citizen participation (Box 17)
    - Committees (Box 17)
    - Committees-minutes and agenda (Box 17)
    - Communication (Box 17)
    - Community (Box 17)
    - Community Chest (Box 17)
    - Community Development (Box 17)
    - Community Research Associates (Box 17)
    - Community Welfare Councils, 2 folders (Box 17)
    - Concepts (Box 17)
    - Conference (method) (Box 17)
    - Conflict (Box 17)
    - Consultation (Box 17)
    - Consumers (Box 17)
    - Cooperative communities (Box 17)
    - Current (Box 17)
    - Curriculum development project (Box 17)
    - Defining Conscientious Objection practice (Box 17)
    - Direct action (Box 17)
    - Direct service agencies (Box 17)
    - Education for (Box 17)
    - Europe (Box 17)
    - Evaluation (Box 17)
    - Executive (Box 18)
    - Field service (Box 18)
    - Foundations (Box 18)
    - Governmental and voluntary agencies (Box 18)
    - Handicapped (Box 18)
    - Health Administration Fellows-Wayne (Box 18)
    - History (Box 18)
    - International Council on Social Welfare (Box 18)
    - Jewish (Box 18)
    - Lectures and addresses
      - 1920s (Box 18)
      - 1930s-1940s (Box 18)
      - 1950s (Box 18)
      - 1960s, 2 folders (Box 18)
      - 1970s (Box 18)
    - Legislation (Box 18)